Miscellaneous Hellenic Studies Collection, 1677-1965: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Miscellaneous Hellenic Studies Collection
1677-1965
C0958
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
1.65 linear feet 1 archival box, 1 oversize flat box
Princeton University. Library. Dept. of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Consists of an open collection of miscellaneous material related to Hellenic Studies.
The collection was established in 2003 to house miscellaneous material related to Helleinic Studies.
The collection consists of miscellaneous material related to Hellenic Studies. There are folders for Jean François Boissonade, Agalia Ionides Coronio, W. N. Glascock, Dora d'Istria, T. Karatheodorēs, Nikos Kazantzakis, Marie-Louis Marcellus, Emmanuel Miller, Constantine Mususrus, Edouard-Jean-Pierre Perrin, Athanasios Petridēs, Abraham Salamé, En Athēnais Epistēmonikē Hetaireia, Viscount Stratford de Redclifffe, E. M. de Vogüé, Sir George Wheler, and Frank A. H. Young. Correspondents include John Boosey, Prince Roland Bonaparte, Edward Burne-Jones, Frederick William Burton, Baron Thomas Denham, Frederika Queen of the Hellenes, Charles Samuel Keene, Vice Admiral Edward Campbell Rich Owen, Edward Poynter, Jacob Spon, and Walter Leaf. Included is a letter (1865) by Emile Crespin regarding the ravages caused by the Cholera epidemic in Constantinople and Thérapia, in Turkey. Also included are letters (1867) by an unidentified French diplomat, posted in Athens, describing trips he has taken around the Mediterranean, to such places as Jerusalem, Cairo, and Constantinople. Zosimas II (1686-1746) is represented by a series of three letters in Latin and Italian (the first signed in Greek) and a Tractatus comprised of sixteen articles in Latin (1736-1737); they were written in the town of Siátista, Macedonia, under Ottoman rule and sent to the Georg Tönnemann, S.J., in Vienna. Later additions include a French autograph manuscript (1946) by Louis Robert describing an archeological trip to Turkey and cotton handkerchief memorializing the Cyprus Convention of 4 June 1878; an autograph album (ca. 1896-1916) of nurse Muriel Bois who worked at the Norland Institute (1906) and the Jenny Lind Infirmary (1907) in England, and who was in Greece (ca. 1914-1916), including watercolor and pencil drawings (a number by children) and contributions by Greek princesses (Olga, Elizabeth, Marina, Margarita, and Theodora); 22 letters (1929-1937) by Prince Nicholas to V. C. Scott O'Connor; and a long letter (1700, copy) by Sieur de Berquin to French administrator Michel Bégon about a diplomatic incident involving French ambassador Charles de Ferriol at the court of Mustafa II in Constantinople.
The oversize box includes nine pencil drawings by Jules Coignet, made during a trip to Greece and Turkey in 1844, including scenes of Smyrna (Turkey), Rhodes (Greece), Beirut (Lebanon).
The folders are arranged alphabetically by author or subject.
The collection is open for research.
The collection was formed as a result of a departmental practice of combining into one collection manuscript material of various accessions relating to a particular author.
Purchased from Roy Davids, Richard Ford, Rodolphe Chamonal, Traces-Ecrites, Librairie Michel Bouvier, Clive Farahar and Sophie Dupre, Petros Vergos, AJASSE Librarie Ancienne, Robert van den Graven in 2003-2011 and gifts from Program in Hellenic Studies with matching funds provided by the Program in Hellenic Studies with the support of the Stanley J. Seeger Hellenic Fund (AM2004-45, 2006-125, 2007-33, 2007-53, 2008-15, 2008-64, 2008-87, 2009-6, 2009-82, 2009-85, 2009-87, 2009-88, 2009-94, 2009-122, 2009-123, 2009-131, 2010-54, 2010-112, 2011-3, 2011-84, 2012-1, 2012-90).
Boissonade, Jean François, 1774-1857 -- Correspondence.; Bégon, Michel -- Correspondence.; Coignet, Jules Louis Philippe, 1798-1860 -- Drawings.; Ferriol, Charles, marquis d'Argental, comte de, 1637-1722 -- Travel -- Turkey -- Istanbul.; Miller, Emmanuel, 1812-1867 --Correspondence.; Nicholas, Prince of Greece, 1872-1938 -- Correspondence.; Societé des Sciences d'Athènes.; Archeology -- Turkey -- History -- Sources.; Art patrons -- England -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Cholera -- Turkey -- History -- 19th century -- Sources.; Diplomatic and consular service, British -- Turkey -- 19th century.; Diplomatic and consular service, French -- Greece -- Athens -- 19th century.; Epidemics -- Turkey -- History -- Sources.; Inscriptions, Greek.; Athens (Greece) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Beirut (Lebanon) -- 19th century -- Pictorial works.; Cairo (Egypt) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Greece -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Greece -- History -- War of Independence, 1821-1829 -- Sources.; Greece -- Politics and government -- 1832-1862.; Istanbul (Turkey) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Istanbul (Turkey) -- History -- Sources.; Izmir (Turkey) -- 19th century -- Pictorial works.; Jerusalem (Israel) -- Description and travel -- 19th century.; Rhodes (Greece) -- 19th century -- Pictorial works.; Tarabya (Turkey) -- History -- Sources.; Turkey -- Description and travel -- 20th century.; Turkey -- History -- Mahmud II, 1808-1839 -- Sources.; Turkey -- History -- Mustafa II, 1695-1703 -- Sources.; Autograph albums -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Drawings -- 19th century.; Hellenic studies
- Berquin, Sieur de, 1700 May 4; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
  ALS (1700, copy) 27 pp., to French administrator Michel Begon about a diplomatic incident involving French ambassador Charles de Ferriol at the court of Mustafa II in Constantinople. AM 2009-94.
- Bois, Muriel, 1896-1916; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Autograph album (ca. 1896-1916), including watercolor and pencil drawings and contributions from several Greek princesses (Elisabeth, Margarita, Olga, Theodora). AM 2009-82.
- Boissonade, Jean Francois, 1774-1857, undated; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
  5 ALsS by Boissonade to fellow Hellenist Jean-Francois Gail (1795-1845) about their translation work. AM 2008-87.
- Bory de Saint-Vincent, 1829-1830; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
  28 ALsS (1829-1830) addressed to Bory de Saint-Vincent, leader of the French expedition to Morea. AM 2010-112.
- Connor, James, 1818-1819; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
  ALS (1819) to his brother Samuel in Dublin. The letter ("No. 2") includes excerpts from his journal, 18 November 1818 - 25 January 1819, describing his experiences on a boat traveling from Malta, to Crete, among the Greek archipelago, and ending in Constantinople. AM 2006-66.
- Coronio, Agalia Ionides, 1834-1906, 1888-1906; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
  5 ALsS to Ms. Coronio from Edward Burne-Jones, Frederick William Burton, Charles Samuel Keene, Edward Poynter, and Walter Leaf; 1 ALS by Edward Poynter to "Miss Ionides," Agalia's sister Helen Euphrosyne ["Nellie"], who later married Dr. William McNeill Whistler, brother of James McNeill Whistler. AM 2004-45.
- Crespin, Emile, 1865; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Lettre de 1865 sur le cholera a Constantinople. AM 2008-15.
- Cyprus Convention, 1878 June 4; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Commemorative handkerchief. AM 2009-6.
- Esnaphia, 1834; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 9)
  11 AMssS from Constantinople dated in 1834 and signed by G. Mantaouranes. AM 2010-115.
- Essai sur les principles de Banque appliques a l'etat actuel de la Grece, 1836; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Printed essay by George Finlay. AM 2011-3.
- Frederika, Queen of the Hellenes, 1917-1981, 1965 March 29; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 11)
  TLS to Robert Goheen, 1965. AM 18545.
- French Diplomat in Athens: Letters, 1867; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 12)
  6 ALs (April - September 1867) describing trips around the Mediterranean, inlcuding Jerusalem, Beirut, Bethlehem, Alexandria, Cairo, Cosntantinople, Smyrna, Athens. AM 2007-53.
- Glascock, W. N. (William Nugent), 1787?-1847, 1845; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 13)
  2 ALsS (1845) to Vice Admiral Edward Campbell Rich Owen. AM 1999-30.
- Guieu, Charles, 1738-1739; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Correspondence book (1738-1739) of French trader based in Smyrna (today's Izmir, Turkey). AM 2011-84.
- Istria, Dora d', comtesse, 1828-1888, 1859 November 3; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 15)
  ALS (1859) to [Emile Littre]. AM 2008-64.
- Kazantzakis, Nikos, 1883-1957, 1849-1905; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 16)
  6 postcards and 8 letters (1849-1965), from Nikos and Helene Kazantzakis to "Banine." AM 1997-2015.
- Karatheodores, T., fl 1880s, 1881; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 17)
  TLS (1881, in Greek) to Athanasios P. Petrides; AMs (1881, in Greek) by Petrides about Etudes sur les Tchinghaines; ou, Bohemiens de l'Empire Ottoman (1870) by A. G. Paspates. AM 1998-37.
- King, Jonas, 1792-1869, 1855 October 2; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 18)
  ALS, Athens, Greece, 2 October 1855, to Michael D. Kalopothakes regarding King's missionary work in Athens. AM 2006 Pyne-Henry.
- Marcellus, Marie-Louis, 1839; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 19)
  ALsS, 1839, 4 pp. total. Drafts of letters to be sent with copies of Souvenirs de l'Orient. Correspondents: David, Bertie Armand, [Dermousseaux] de Givre, Nettement de la Mode, Le Cte de Partoret, de Genoade. AM 2006-125.
- Miller, E, 1856 November 12; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 20)
  ALS (n.d.) to "Mon cher Monsieur" regarding teh date of a Greek inscription; ALS (12 November 1856) to a collaborator of Brosset. AM 2005-94.
- Miller, Emmanuel, 1812-1886, 1845-1867; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 21)
  18 ALsS to various correspondents, 1845-1867. AM 2009-85.
- "Miraculous relic in Cyprus", 1725 August 2; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Anonymous letter, 2 August 1725.
- Musurus, Constantine, 1807-1891, 1886 February 3; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 23)
  ALS (1886) to Baron Thomas Denman. AM 1999-30.
- Nicholas, prince of Greece, 1872-1938, 1929-1937; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 24)
  22 ALsS and ACsS (1929-1937) to V. C. Scott O'Connor. AM 2009-82.
- Notes, 1835; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Report on the Greek politcal leades in 1835. AM 2011-3.
- Perrin, Edouard-Jean-Pierre, 1852-1926, 1872; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 26)
  6 ALsS (May - October, 1872) by Perrin to his parents, while he was a student in the l'Ecole Navale he sails in the Aegean, visiting such places a sAthens and Smyrna. AM 2007-33.
- Phildelpheus, Alexandros, 1899; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Autograph Greek manuscript (1899), 11 pp. Lecture or study on the visit of "The Apostle Paul in Areios Pagos." AM 2009-122.
- Robert, Louis, 1946; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Manuscript d'un voyage archeologique en Turquie, 1946. AM 2008-15.
- Salame, Abraham, fl. 1816, 1821-1828; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 29)
  ALS (1828) to John Boosey; 4 ALsS (1821, n.d.) to unidentified persons. AM 1999-30.
- Samos [L'ile grecque de Samos deviant principaute turque], 1835; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 30)
  AMs. AM 2011-3.
- Societe des Sciences d'Athenes, 1894-1908; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Printed brochure of organization (1894), membership letter (1908) for Roland Bonaparte, and cover letter (n.d., in French) accompanying the 2 items. AM 2005-96.
- Stratford de Redcliffe, Stratford Canning, Viscount, 1786-1880, 1826 May 25; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 32)
  LS (1826) to "Captain Admilton," written from Cosntantinople, regarding the future of Greece and Turkey. AM 2002-127.
- Su l'etat Financier de la Grece, 1835; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 33)
  AMs (ca. 1835-1836) on the financial state of Greece in 1835. AM 2011-3.
- Soustos, Michael Vodas, 1828-1839; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 34)
  9 ALs, 1828-1829.
- Tableau d'importation et d'exportation de commune general de l'ile de Crete, 1834; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 35)
  D, table. AM 2010-54.
- Tachtses, Kostas, 1954-1988; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Correspondence with Ben Sonnenberg and other materials. AM 1997-107, 2002-110.
- Theotokes, Emmanouel Baron, 1821 September 17; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 37)
  ALS to Charles Peroy in London, 17 September 1821. AM 1997-108.
- Vogue, E. M. de, 1887; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 38)
  "Lettres Atheniennes, par Mr. le Cte. Charles de Mouy, Librarie Plon, 1887," AMsS, 9 pp. AM 2005-95.
- Wheler, George, Sir, 1650-1723, 1677 March 22; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 39)
  ALS (1677, in French) to Jacob Spon. AM 2005-40.
- Young, Frank A. H, 1860-1861; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 40)
  2 ALsS (1860, 1861) to "Mrs. Dunham" describing his missionary life in Turkey (Constantinople, Trebizond). AM 2005-95.
- Zosimus II, 1736-1737; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 41)
  3 letters (1736-1737) to Georg Tonneman, S.J.; 1 document, 1736. AM 1997-104.
- Miscellaneous Oversize, 1836; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 1)
  One autograph Greek manuscript letter; one diploma of membership in the Athenian Society of Natural History; two broadsides of statutes of the Society in Greek and German [c. 1836]. AM 2009-131.
- Coignet, Jules Louis Philippe, 1798-1860, 1844; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 2)
  9 pencil drawings by Coignet, made during a trip to Greece and Turkey in 1844, including scenes of Smyrna (Turkey), Rhodes (Greece), Beirut (Lebanon). AM 2009-87.
- Karatza, Roxane, 1894; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Watercolor of the genalogic tree of the family Mavroyeni (1894); watercolor of the genealogic tree of the family Antoine Rosetti; watercolor of the genealogic tree of the family Callimachi; watercolor of the genealogic tree of the family Diamanti Draco Soutzo (c. 1894). AM 2009-123.